大多数人躲避伤害 努力求生
Most people go through life trying to not get hit.
- 你还好吗 - 很好
- What's up man? - All good.
你看清动作要领了吗
Did you see that fight?
我想我本可以赢的
Oh did I? I think I could've won.
秘诀是要躲避拳头
The trick is to roll with the punches
并且祈祷不要被打倒
and hope that you don't get floored by one.
再来一次
Again.
我们的世界在风暴中诞生
Our world was born out of violence...
这场风暴一开始就横行肆虐
and a storm that has raged since the beginning of time.
它有可以摧毁整个星球的力量
A storm with the power to destroy planets.
一次强劲的碰撞能改变一切
One mighty collision can change everything.
已有先例 亦能重演
It's done it before and it could do it again.
众人临安颓厦 如燕处危巢却又浑然不知
Most of us live in blissful ignorance of the chaos around us.
但有八名宇航员 通过在太空中的千日之旅
But, eight astronauts with over 1,000 days in space between them
告诉我们 身处外太空
can tell us how being "up there"
是如何改变自己对地球的看法的
helped them to truly understand what goes on down here.
国家地理  倾情呈现
太空中 每天都有约40吨的物质
Everyday the earth ploughs through about 40 tons
掠过地球上空
of material in space.
达伦·阿罗诺夫斯基 大作
太空异常活跃
There is so much activity,
事件层出不穷 而地球正处其中
so much action and our planet is right in the middle of it.
理想 之作
太空并不空空如也
Space isn't vast and empty space
而是个不断运动着的宇宙风暴
but a dynamic, cosmic storm.
由 威尔·史密斯 主持
一场能毁灭我们的风暴
It's a storm that could kill us,
但如果没有它
but without it...
我们也就不复存在
we wouldn't be here at all.
这是个由奇异结合
This is a story about the weird connections,
天缘凑巧
the near misses
蓬勃迸发
the lucky breaks
创造出这神奇世界的故事
that created this amazing world.
45亿年来 我们的星球被重创
For 4.5 billion years our planet has been battered and
被擦伤 被打击 但我们仍然屹立不倒
bruised and punched and pummeled but we're still standing.
这是场铸就自我的战争
It's actually the battle that's built us
一个久远的故事
and this is the tale of the tape.
被点亮的星球
谢了伙计 很好
Thanks guys, awesome. Alright.
妮可·斯托特是个工程师 飞行员 还是个...
Nicole Stott is an engineer, pilot and oh yeah...
酷吗
These are cool uh?
她曾在太空生活过三个月
She lived for three months in space.
你可以戴上试试
You can even stick your hand in it.
妮可·斯托特
漫游太空104天
左手
Left hand.
好了 我出来了
Okay I'm coming out.
妮可 把你的右腰绳系到前面的UIAD环上
Nicole, your right waist tether to the forward UIAD ring.
她真是个狠角色
Frankly she's a bad ass.
想象在高压环境下
Now imagine them all pressurized
你得十分用力才能活动它
and you're having to work against it really hard.
太空运输系统 128号太空行走任务 妮可·斯托特
难以置信 我曾在那里
Here I was, it was so unbelievable.
20年来 我一直投身于飞行器制造
I'd spent almost 20 years helping build spaceships
彼时 我就在其中一个里...
and now here I was myself on one...
真是神奇
just amazing.
我这里没问题 妮可
Okay I am clear Nicole.
还记得看我太空行走的事吗
Remember watching me do a spacewalk?
记得
Yeah.
- 觉得好玩吗 - 很害怕 - 害怕什么呢
- Yeah. Was that fun? - Scary. -Yeah, why was it scary?
怕你掉下来
Cause I thought you were gonna fall off.
当你在太空中时 你离地球有250英里远
When you're in space, 250 miles above our planet
看着眼前的景象 你就会发现
and looking at these things you thought you knew,
这是个全新的视野
you see them in a totally new way.
风  暴
举例来说 我第一次看到太空来的流星
For example, the first time I saw a shooting star
这种特别的视觉体验提醒了我
from the space station was this very visual reminder that
有很多其他的物质
there's a lot of other things traveling
在同一空间中穿行
through the same space, in space.
第一次看到这样的景象
What did I see and the first time I saw it,
使我大吃一惊
it kind of startled me was,
一颗流星正从我们下方穿过
a shooting star coming in below us.
那是颗奔向地球的小行星
That's a micro meteorite coming into the earth and
在大气层燃烧起来
burning up in the atmosphere and you see this sort of
迈克·马西米诺
漫游太空29天
一场正在上演的烟火秀
firework display thing going on.
我正在观测地球
I was doing earth observation
杰瑞·林格恩
漫游太空143天
正拍照时 我忽然看到
and I'm taking a photo and all of a sudden I see a hole
太阳能电池板上出现了一个这么大的洞
just magically appear about that big in the solar panel, you know,
可能是被一粒沙击中造成的
that was probably hit by a grain of sand,
一粒粒这么小的东西
something that size,
在不同轨道上 以每小时28000千米的速度袭来
coming at 17,500 miles an hour in a different orbit.
你可能随时被陨石袭击
You get hit by rocks all the time,
克里斯·哈德菲尔德
漫游太空166天
你能听到它们在飞船表面来回穿梭
you can hear them ricocheting off the hull.
你能看到它们在飞船玻璃上留下的痕迹
You can see the scars of them in the windows of the spaceship.
难以想象
It's a little mind boggling,
外面究竟有多少陨石
when you think about how much is really out there.
很多时候 这些东西都很小
Mostly the stuff up there is pretty small,
在大气层燃烧殆尽 没什么影响
burns up in the atmosphere, nothing to get worked up about,
但也会有很大的陨石出现
but there are some pretty big rocks up there too,
比如造访恐龙的那颗
ask the dinosaurs.
6700 万 年 前
我们认为 造成恐龙灭绝的小行星
We believe the asteroid that caused the extinction of the dinosaurs
正是跨越太阳系而来
started way out in the solar system.
彼此间距离之远
You know, travelling that distance,
而能够不可思议地对地球进行精确打击
it's incredible that it found this target of earth.
这是恐龙的灾难 但对我们而言 未尝不是件好事
Bad for the dinosaurs but ultimately good for us.
我们都自认为了解这个故事
We all think we know this story,
但在事发之处 墨西哥丛林
but there's something special about the place where it happened,
有些特别的东西
in the jungles of Mexico.
犹卡坦
墨西哥
在这 我有机会下潜至
Here in Mexico I have the chance to dive in
这世上最奇妙的自由潜水点
what is the most magical place to free dive in the entire world.
纪尧姆·奈瑞
自由潜水大师
小行星的猛烈撞击
This incredible place was created with
造就了这里
very strong violence when the asteroid hits.
而如今此地却如此静谧 与之大相迳庭
And the result of this is this calm place, this paradox.
此地此刻的安宁 也无法掩盖
This place which is now very quiet was, at some point,
曾在这里发生的戏剧性事件
where something dramatic happened.
生命差点就此消失
Life almost disappeared.
但与此同时 我们的故事又在这里开始
But at the same time, this is where our story started and
这是我们如今能够存在的原因
this is why we are here now.
当扫描这片区域时
When this area was scanned,
我们看到了数百个这样的水坑
we saw that hundreds of these flooded Mexican caverns
它们彼此相连形成了一个极大的半圆
connected together into a vast semi-circle.
这个巨型陨石坑的边缘
The edges of a huge crater,
有177千米宽 近20千米深
110 miles across and 12 miles deep.
一颗体积如此巨大的小行星 撞击地球的任何地点
An asteroid that big hitting the planet anywhere
都将带来毁灭性的后果 但是科学家认为
is going to be devastating, but scientists think
正因为撞击地点的独特 才更具毁灭性
it was especially devastating because of where it hit.
正中靶心般 撞到了一片硫磺储量极大的区域
A bulls eye strike on a large Sulphur reserve.
硫矿升华
The Sulphur rock vaporized
[物态变化中 物质从固态直接转换为气态的现象称为"升华"]
使得数百亿吨的污染气体
sending billions of tons of polluting gas
涌入了大气中
into the atmosphere...
遮蔽了阳光
blocking out the sun.
地球急剧变冷 恐龙灭绝了
The earth froze and the dinosaurs died.
这颗古老的大块头小行星
So this big old asteroid has been journeying
在完成天地大冲撞前 已在太空中穿行了百亿年
for billions of years through space before it gets to us
而地球是会自转的
and the earth spins right.
所以如果这颗陨石在数秒后到达
So if the rock had arrived just a few seconds later,
它就会坠入深海 脱离靶心
it would have crashed out in the deep ocean, no bulls eye,
不会有烈焰风暴 恐龙也不会灭绝
no firestorm, no dino extinction.
地球的过往有太多这样的时刻
Earth's history is full of moments like this.
这是一个兼具灭亡与好运的神话
It's a tale of destructive good fortune
它连接着一个星球的死亡
that connects the death of a planet,
千万只非洲蝙蝠
ten million African bats,
天空中的里程表
a clock in the sky
以及太阳系诞生之初的小陨石
and tiny rocks from the birth of our solar system,
就如我拳头般大小
some about the size of my fist.
撞击地球的陨石不计其数
There's a lot of rocks hitting us from space.
如果它们穿过大气层 撞击地表
If they make it through our atmosphere and hit the surface of our planet,
人们就四处会搜寻这些陨石
people go in search of these
无论天涯海角
in very remote places to try to find them.
它们极具价值 因为它们是
They're extremely valuable because they contain really
地球诞生进程的见证
the story of where our earth came from.
在数百亿年后
砰
Boom!
他来了
厄尔切比沙丘
摩洛哥
欢迎 欢迎 欢迎
你发现这个的地方
附近肯定还有
孩子们需要回去
检查一下
在摩洛哥 每年都有传言一些
In Morocco we have a couple of buzzes every year of
亚当·阿伦森
陨石商人
超级酷 超级棒的陨石出现
something that's way cool, a super awesome meteorite.
如果有陨石在荒漠中被发现 然后消息传出
If a meteorite is found in the desert and word gets out...
尤其有小道消息说它极其贵重的
Especially if it's of extreme value.
然后在这就会形成"淘金热"
Then there is like a gold rush.
我们谈论的 是构建我们星球的石头
We're talking about the building blocks of our planet.
一些碳质球粒陨石最具价值
Some of the most valuable meteorites are carbonaceous chondrite meteorites.
它们是太阳系中最久远的固体形式
They're the oldest form of solid material in the solar system.
所有的大学 以及博物馆都想拥有它
All the universities want it, all the museums want it.
贝都十分善于鉴定这些陨石
The Bedouins are getting amazingly good at recognizing these things.
你带了什么
我给你带了一颗陨石
是真的陨石吗
绝对是真的
在哪找到的
很近  就在陶斯附近
是球粒状陨石
开个价吧
你报个价吧
一克70迪拉姆
[迪拉姆:摩洛哥货币,1迪拉姆≈1.7人民币元]
门外汉看来 这些就是普通的石头
To the untrained eye, these might just look like a normal rock,
但古老陨石里却蕴含着能够构建一个
but the really old ones contain all the raw materials
如地球般行星的全部原材料
to build a planet like earth.
46亿年前 地球如今所在的位置
4.6 billion years ago where earth is today,
仅是一片围绕着新生太阳旋转的
there was just a giant cloud of gas and dust,
浩瀚烟尘
all swirling around the new born sun.
星 尘
46 亿 年 前
这是宇宙风暴的开端
This was where the cosmic storm started.
首先 极小的颗粒被静电力吸引
First off with tiny particles attracted by an electrostatic force.
这是个缓慢的过程 但最终凝结成固体
It's a slow process but eventually clumps grew into solid matter.
虽然仍只有沙粒般大小
Still only as big as a grain of sand,
但在其自身引力的作用下
but now with just enough gravity of their own
微粒间互相结合
to pull other grains in.
逐渐融合成了石块
These grains fused into rocks
随着撞击和凝结
and as they smashed and clumped
这些碰撞加剧
the collisions grew in intensity.
在极高的热量和压强下
Under immense heat and pressure,
这些石块开始组建我们的地球
the rocks began to build our planet.
地球形成的原理似乎非常简单
There seems to be nothing subtle about the way earth was built.
这就像用一把大锤
It would almost be like building a space station
建造一个空间站
with a sledgehammer.
所有这些微粒撞击在一起
All those bits smashing together,
即是构建出如今地球的一切所需
they were everything we needed to build a living planet.
我们骨骼中的钙 婚戒中的金
The calcium in our bones, the gold in our wedding rings,
甚至是船体的铁 从地球的诞生之初就在这里
even the iron in our ships was all here from the beginning,
仅除一项紧缺 那就是水
except one thing was in short supply, water,
但它那时已经在路上了 并且马上就到
but it was on its way and coming in fast.
被点亮的星球
很多宇航员都会告诉你
A lot of astronauts will tell you
自从六岁时看到登月行动的那一刻
that from six years old watching the moon landing that they knew from
妮可·斯托特
漫游太空104天
他们就知道宇航员
that moment on that astronaut was a job
是他们渴望的工作
that they wanted to do.
对我来说 不是这么回事
For me, it wasn't that way.
我的背景是航空工程
My background is aeronautical engineering.
我渴望做与飞行相关的事
I wanted to do something with flying
可以让我学到事物升空的原理
that allowed me to learn about how things fly
如果你想了解事物是如何飞上天的
and then ultimately if you wanna know how things fly,
就不可能不想知道火箭是如何起飞的
I can't imagine not wanting to know how rocket ships fly.
2009年8月28日
于是某天有人打电话给我说
And then one day I got this phone call
我被指定在国际空间站中
to say that I was assigned to fly a long duration flight
进行一次长期飞行作业
on the International Space Station.
妮可原本不打算上空间站
Nicole didn't set out to fly on the ISS,
她是空间站的建造师
her job was to build the thing,
即便她上到了太空中 满脑子也都是设计
but once she got up there, she still had an eye for design.
所以身为一名工程师
So as an engineer you can imagine,
在我看向地球时 不得不好奇
I couldn't help but look at the earth and wonder,
它是怎么运转的
how does that work?
望向地球时 有一点显而易见
What's blindingly obvious when you look at earth,
水是关键
is water is the key.
但早期的地球 并不是我如今所见的蓝色星球
But earlier it didn't look like this blue planet that I saw,
那是一块干燥荒芜的巨石
it was a dry and barren rock.
为了生命的兴盛
For life to thrive like it has done,
地球需要外界的水源
the earth needed delivery of water.
我们认为地球成型后不久
We believe soon after the earth was formed,
瓦拉纳西
印度
水就从外太空疯狂袭来
our water came from space in a hail of violence.
那情景想必非常凶猛
It must have been brutal.
我们猜测这暴雨下了一亿年左右
We think it lasted for about 100 million years.
由冰组成的彗星和小行星再次撞向地球
Icy comets and asteroids collided with the planet again.
从而给予了我们水
To supply us with that top off of water.
火 星
然而不像同被暴雨轰炸过的火星和金星
But unlike Mars and Venus, who were surely bombarded by the same storm,
金 星
地球留住了水
we kept our water.
幸运的是
As luck would have it,
造就当今地球样貌的原石
the seed that would one day grow, into the earth we know it.
在距离太阳最合适的轨道上安定了下来
found its place at the perfect distance from the sun,
也就是我们常说的 "宜居带"
what we now call the Goldilocks zone.
金凤花姑娘(Goldilocks):金凤花姑娘喜欢不冷不热的粥,不软不硬的椅子.即"刚刚好"的东西.
所以后来美国人常用金凤花姑娘来形容"刚刚好"
既不太热 也不太冷
Not too hot, not too cold.
太阳系是浩瀚的
The solar system is vast.
地球上的每一滴水 原本都很可能
Earth could have easily wound up somewhere where every drop
被冻住 或者被蒸发掉
of water either froze up or boiled away.
但在这里 水却可以长期以固液气三态共存
But here it's solid, gas and liquid all the time.
只需要像日出这样细小的变化就能够
It only takes a tiny change like a sunrise for things to
让冰开始融化
get a little bit slippery.
此地为全程340米的徒手自由攀冰经典线路
瑞 士
对我来说 攀冰最具刺激的一点是
它的本质是水
冰的构造每年都在变
没有哪年是一样的
它永远都在变化 所以每一次攀登都是独特的经历
托马斯·桑弗
登山者
当然 如果温度在零上的话
冰就会开始融化
你不知何时它会崩塌
固态 液态 气态
Solid, liquid, gas.
地球上的水 可谓变形金刚
Earth's water, it's a shape shifter,
时刻变化着状态 从冰雪变成海水
constantly changing forms and as it moves from snow to sea,
从小溪变成蒸汽 进而创造出天气
from stream to steam it helps make the weather that
让地球如同天堂
keeps this planet a paradise for life.
在太空中你可以看到亚马逊流域上空的积云
From space you can see clouds at the tops of the Amazon Basin
你还可以看到积云在大海上空蒸发
but you can also see them evaporating on the oceans
利兰梅尔文
漫游太空24天
所以这是一个相互连接的系统
and so these systems are all interconnected.
那看似必然的自然过程
That natural, seemingly inevitable process
查里斯·哈德菲尔德
漫游太空166天
将大海转变为降雨
of turning the oceans into rain,
那正是地球生命的精髓
it's the very essence of life itself on earth.
没有这过程 就没有河流 没有地下水
Without it they'd be no rivers, no ground water,
没有植物 动物
no plants, no animals.
梅·杰米森
漫游太空8天
大地就不会有生命
The continents would be dead.
地球不断的变化使我感到惊讶
It actually surprised me how dynamic the planet is,
风云变幻 雷鸣电闪 广布于地表
clouds whirling, lightning storms propagating over the surface,
可以看见洋流运动 你从而发现
the ocean currents visible and you realize this
杰里·林恩格
漫游太空143天
脚下并不是一块死气沉沉的石头 它是有生命的
thing is not a dead rock down there, this thing is alive.
我想我们可以庆幸
So we can thank our lucky stars I suppose
我们的地球刚好处于
that the seed that started earth was in the right place
水能够以三种形态存在的位置
for water to exist in its three states.
我们的星球从宇宙尘埃中诞生
Our planet was born out of cosmic dust
随后被外来的暴雨浇灌
then watered by a storm from above,
不过与分裂地球的撞击相比
but all those blows were nothing compared to one that
这些根本算不上什么
literally ripped the earth apart.
其实地球曾是有兄弟的
You see earth had a twin.
一个威胁到我们存在的孪生兄弟
A twin that threatened our existence.
被点亮的星球
地球由许许多多次撞击而形成
The earth is the result of many, many collisions
但最猛烈的一次撞击
but the most violent collision of all
人类一度知之甚少
was unknown to humankind, unknown that is,
直到我们登上了月球
until we went to the moon.
1969年7月
我对首次登月成功深有印象
I have really vivid memories of our first moon landing.
坐在黑白电视机跟前
Sitting in front of the black and white TV,
妮可·斯科特
漫游太空104天
不知为何 我还记得当时正吃着烤奶酪三明治
for some reason I remember having a grilled cheese sandwich, who knows?
我们原本以为 色彩缤纷的地球
We thought, how could there possibly be anything in common
和灰突突的月球之间是不可能会有
between the earth and all its beautiful earthly colors
任何共通之处的
and the grey of the moon.
尼尔 从这里看实在是美丽
Oh that looks beautiful from here Neil.
这坑坑洼洼的表面
This cratered surface.
和地球不同 但还是非常漂亮
It's different but it's very pretty out here.
我们的发现使大家震惊了
What we found surprised us,
月球和地球上的岩石有着惊人的相似之处
moon rock and earth rock had striking similarities.
你可以继续执行任务
We'd like you to press on.
好的
Yeah right.
暗示着地球和月球似乎同源
Suggesting that both the earth and the moon had somehow originated from the same place.
这是个人的一小步
It's one small step for man...
这种结果的造成只能有几种可能
Well there's only a handful of ways that could have happened
这几种可能都不太美观
and none of 'em are pretty.
最著名的理论是
The prominent theory
宜居带里原本还有另外一个天体
is that there was something else in the Goldilocks zone.
还有一个叫做忒伊亚的行星
Another planet called Theia
与地球在相交的轨道上
and it was on an intersecting orbit with earth.
在太空中 当两个物体处于相交轨道
In space when two things are in an intersecting orbit,
而且时间足够久 就会无法避免地相撞
with enough time, it's inevitable that those two things will collide.
它们在撞击的时候熔化
Both planets became molten on impact.
满是抛向外太空的碎片
We have debris thrown out into space.
当这堆碎片最终冷却下来后
When this cloud of debris eventually cools,
它就浓缩成了一个新的天体
it condenses into a new cosmic partnership.
地球 和一个巨大的月球
Planet earth and a uniquely large moon.
月球就像从我们这里剥离出来的
Our moon was ripped right out of us,
因为如此
because of that,
它又大又近 还有着强引力
it's big and close and has a lot of pull,
它引起潮起潮落 造就了潮汐 不是吗
pulls the sea in, pulls the sea out, tides, simple right?
但当海上覆盖着冰的时候
But things get harder when that same sea
事情就没那么简单了
is covered by ice.
韦 克 姆 贝
加拿大 魁北克
这是爷爷熟识
Which is something that granddads know
洛卡斯·拿帕阿录克
高龄爱斯基摩人
而当代孩子即将学到的
and modern kids could stand to learn.
孩子们一定要知道
月亮的能力
孙子
什么
要涨潮了
这些贻贝
可不够全家人吃啊
还有很多食物
就在冰下面
但是你得知道什么时候去抓
当月亮变作满月时
水就流远了
洛卡斯知道 月盈则潮盛
LukasI knows,when the moon is full,the tide is strongest
此时他们能在冰下多待几分钟
and he'll have a few more minutes under the ice,
这是他们的好机会
the best chance to grab their catch.
赶紧多捡点
在那儿
你听到了吗
快 我们快走
我们不该低估
We shouldn't underestimate how influential
月亮对我们生活的影响
the moon is in all of our lives.
规律性的潮汐也给了我们另一种节奏
Those regular tides also help give us another kind of rhythm,
可能你以为它一直如此
one you might assume had been with us all along.
形成月球的那次冲撞
The collision that ended up forming the moon
使得地球飞速旋转
sent the earth just spinning.
当时的一天只有5个小时
A day back then was just five hours long.
是潮汐作用最终使得地球慢下来
It was the drag of the tides that eventually slowed the earth down
变成了一天24个小时
to where a day became 24 hours,
正如我们现在知道的
like we know now.
24小时一天 起床  吃早饭
The 24-hour day; waking up, having breakfast,
工作八小时
working eight hours.
做晚饭 日复一日
Making dinner, day in, day out.
那些循环 已经写入了我们的基因
These cycles, they're embedded in our DNA.
那次重击创造出了月亮
The violent whack that gave us our moon,
潮汐和一天24小时
our tides and our 24-hour day,
其实还有一个东西
it gave us one more thing too;
费城的夏天
summer in Philadelphia.
被点亮的星球
我印象中的宇宙空间站
When I think of the space station,
就像一幅在宇宙中的杰作
I think of this, like, beautiful masterpiece in space,
妮可·斯托特
飞机工程师
挂在那里
just hanging there.
工程上最大的难题是
The ultimate engineering challenge was,
怎么让太空飞船环境尽可能地像地球
how do ya make your spaceship as much like earth as possible?
第一次从舱门穿梭进
Crossing the hatch from the space shuttle
宇宙空间站的时候
into the space station the first time.
我还记得我心里想 哇 这地方
I remember thinking, wow, it's not the neatest
可真乱
place I've ever seen.
那里有电缆 电线 电脑
There was wires and cables  and computers
和挂在墙上的各种设备
and equipment all strung along these walls.
我们在那里 根本是在模仿
The way we live there is, we've essentially mimicked
我们在地球上生活的方式
what we have naturally occurring on our planet.
我们得制造氧气来呼吸
We have to generate the oxygen to breathe.
我们得发电去发动我们的系统
We have to generate the electricity to power all of our systems.
我们必须找出净化空气的方法
We have to figure out a way to clean the air,
这样我们才能继续呼吸
so we can continue to breathe.
我们人类要想生活的舒适
Because we're human beings and can only live comfortably
就只能在一定的温度范围内
really within a certain temperature range,
整个宇宙空间站系统都运行的前提下
the whole space station, all of the systems are working
要维持这样的环境很难
really hard to maintain that environment for us.
然后你看向地球 就会发现
And then you look down at earth and you realize that's
这正是大自然所做的 想想就觉得了不起
exactly what nature is doing, just on a mind-blowing scale.
那次天地大冲撞造就了月亮
And we've got that cosmic collision that made our moon
真多亏了它
to thank for it.
哇
Wow.
地球和忒伊亚之间的撞击太过强烈
That collision between earth and Theia was so violent
以至于地球都被撞歪了
that it actually knocked earth off its axis.
看
There you go.
假设 这是太阳
So let's just pretend, this is our sun
这是地球 地球由于撞击
and this is our earth and our earth is titled,
倾斜了23.5度
due to that collision, titled 23 and a half degrees.
半年的时间 北半球
For six months of the year the northern hemisphere is
接受太阳直射 另外半年
favoring the sun and for six months of the year,
南半球被太阳直射
the southern hemisphere is favoring the sun.
太阳直射点能在一年中完从北到南的转移
The shift in the sun's energy from north to south throughout the year
从最热的地方移动到最冷的
is constantly trying to move the hot areas to the cold areas
再从最冷的地方移动到最热的
and the cold areas to the hot areas.
地轴的这一倾角形成了四季
This tilt of the earth results in our seasons.
季节逐渐改变了地表的
The seasons constantly change in shape and contour
克里斯·哈德菲尔德
漫游太空166天
形状和轮廓
the land underneath.
这个世界始终在不停变动
The world is constantly adjusting itself.
从太空中的有利位置
From the vantage point of space
你可以看到雪域
you can see the ever-changing planet through the seasons
利兰·梅尔文
漫游太空24天
通过季节变化成为荒漠
from snow-capped mountains to desert plains.
我从没想过这件事 直到最近
I really never thought of this until just very recently
我同时看到了四季
you know, I'm seeing all the seasons at once,
杰瑞·林格恩
漫游太空143天
我在北半球看到了冬天
so I'm seeing the winter in the northern hemisphere and
在南半球看到了夏天
it's summer in the southern hemisphere.
若地球不倾斜 就会有半个地球
If we had no tilt, nearly half the planet could
全年封冻
be frozen all year round.
妮可所处的佛罗里达位于赤道附近 影响不大
Nicole would be fine in Florida nearer the equator but
但在费城长大的我 将在后院拥有一座冰川
growing up in Philly, there'd be a glacier in my backyard.
因为黄赤交角的存在 这个星球上
Because of our tilt, there really are few places on this planet
很少有生命无法生存的地方
where life can't thrive.
我们星球上的生命已经与季节同步
Life on our planet has synchronized with our seasons.
在春天养育幼崽
Raising its young in the spring
并为过冬做准备
and readying them for winter.
45亿年前
Four and a half billion years ago
一次撞击导致了地球倾斜 进而创造了季节
we started with a smash that created a tilt that made our seasons,
给予了我们生存的韵律
that gave us the rhythms of existence.
但更重要的是
But more than that,
那次撞击赋予了我们周围生命的多样性
it gave us the diversity of life we see around us.
大约六点零五分
第一只蝙蝠开始出洞
就好像有人发出了信号
弗兰克·威廉姆斯
自然环境保护主义者
很快变成数百只
还没等你反应过来 天空已经有了数百万只
赞比亚
卡桑卡
这是地球上最大规模的哺乳动物迁徙
他们飞向各个方向
遮住了两万五千多平方千米的天空
很难想象 一年中的大部分时间里
Hard to imagine but for most of the year,
没有一只蝙蝠在这里生活
not a single one of these bats lives here.
这一千万只蝙蝠都是从非洲来的
All ten million arrive from across Africa,
它们追逐雨水 奔着成熟的水果而来
chasing the rains, to gorge on ripening fruits.
每天晚上
他们都会吃掉量达自身体重一半的水果
设想一下 有上千万的蝙蝠
大约每晚就需要一千万吨的水果
他们吃水果同时还会吃下种子
吃完后他们会飞行一段距离
或许五十到一百公里
与此同时
种子会穿过消化系统
最终落到森林地面上某处
我们可以看到数十亿种子飞跃大陆
从本质上来说 这些蝙蝠是森林的投递系统
These bats are essentially a flying forest delivery system.
地球的倾斜意味着冷转热 热转冷
The tilt of the earth means cold moves to hot and hot to cold,
意味着春天代替冬天 正如夏天屈服于秋天
means winter gives way to spring just as summer yields to fall.
还意味着蝙蝠飞跃大陆 为森林播种
It means bats fly across a continent seeding forests as they go.
这世界千丝万缕的联系
The world is connected in 1,000 ways
都源于那场猛烈的撞击
and all because of one massive whack.
所以危险都已不复存在了吗
So is the danger all the in past
还是另一场暴风雨前的平静
or is the calm before another storm?
被点亮的星球
这个星球之所以存在
This planet is only here
是因为我们已经遭受了足够的打击
because we've weathered just enough body blows to build our world.
目前为止 是场那完美风暴 创造了我们的完美家园
So far it's been a perfect storm that's made our perfect home,
它给人一种稳定 安全 可靠的感觉
one that feels stable, safe, reliable.
然而并非如此
It isn't.
想象你在一条船上
Imagine yourself on a boat.
在大洋的中心
Out in the middle of the ocean.
大不列颠西部海防区
北 大 西 洋
处于风暴眼中
In the middle of a storm.
一场大风暴
A big storm.
它对你来说特别真实
It's very real to you.
甚至可能会有一点恐怖
It might even be a little bit scary.
但如果你有机会去聚焦
But if you had the opportunity to just zoom in
其中一滴水珠
on one of these tiny little droplets
一窥那滴水里生活的微生物
and see that inside that little droplet  are these tiny little micro-organisms
它们并没有注意到周围发生的这场风暴
that are just oblivious to this storm going on around them.
如果我们着眼于我们的地球 着眼于我们生存的地方
And if we look at our earth, if we look at where we live,
这一颗在宇宙中普普通通的星球
this planet that's out in space,
我们会以某种方式过着日常生活
we in some ways go about our daily lives
而不去注意在我们周围 在太空中
oblivious to all the action that's going on around us, in space,
在太阳系中 在宇宙中发生的一切
in the solar system, in the universe.
这场从本质上来看非常猛烈的宇宙风暴
This cosmic storm that actually has a violent nature to it,
正是我们在这里的原因
is the reason why we're here.
是我们能够在这个星球上
The reason why we're able to live
如此舒服地生活的原因
so comfortably on this planet.
在太空飞行之前 我非常努力地向
Before flying in space I tried really hard to learn from
曾经踏上过太空的人学习
the people who had flown before me,
去感受飞行经历对他们的意义
to get some idea of what the experience meant to them.
这些宇航员已经从太空中看到了整个地球
These astronauts had seen the whole earth from space.
当他们把地球描绘成一个极其美丽的地方时
While they described it as a really incredibly beautiful place,
总有人会说
there were also some that said,
感觉自己十分渺小
they felt a sense of insignificance.
在很早的时候 当我望向窗外
From the very first time I looked out the window,
我就觉得这一切意义非凡
I felt like this is significant.
它对于我的意义在于
The significance of it to me
弄清这美丽的星球 是如何从混沌
is how something so overwhelmingly beautiful could have come from chaos,
暴力 和碰撞中产生的
violence and collisions.
想想这巧妙的尺度
It's just amazing to think about this fine line, this,
这事关能否在这里繁衍生息的平衡
this balance between being here surviving,
想想就不可思议
thriving and not.
风暴不是我们的敌人
The storm has not been our enemy.
没有它 我们也不会在这里
We aren't here in spite of it.
正因为它 我们才能在这里
We're here because of it.
当风暴平息时
And when the storm blows over,
只剩蓝天和彩虹
it's anything but blue skies and rainbows.
下一集
Next time...
该聊聊太阳了
Here comes the sun.
太阳是生命的燃料
It is the fuel of life,
但它不是我们的朋友
but it is not our friend.
而是个星球杀手
The sun is a planet killer.